(bright music)
- The Boeing VC-25
is perhaps the most
iconic plane in the world,
and it is of course the aircraft
that the US president most
often uses while traveling,
giving it the call sign Air Force One.
(bright music continues)
But there is also a lesser known aircraft
that is just as vital
to the president, one
that hopefully would
never need to be used.
This is the Boeing E-4B, better
known as the Doomsday Plane,
and its nickname is not
exaggerated, as the plane was made
for nuclear war.
(energetic music)
A plane built for the end of the world,
designed to survive when
everything else fails,
able to command an
entire war from the sky,
and packed with technology
the public almost never sees.
And for this video, I
digitally reconstructed
and mapped out the inside
(video whooshes)
of the aircraft to understand
how the Doomsday Plane actually works.
(bright music)
The Doomsday Plane exists to
solve one very unique problem.
What if the United States
hit by a nuclear attack?
This hypothetical scenario
became very real during the 1950s
and '60s when the Cold War
tension was at its peak.
Both the US and the Soviet Union
were amassing massive
stockpiles of nuclear warheads,
and both nations were
proving that they can strike
the other nation, with the United States
stationing nuclear missiles in Europe,
and during the Cuban missile crisis,
the Soviet Union placing
their missiles in Cuba.
During this time, the
United States established
a complex system of protocols
for how it would actually carry out
a nuclear strike against an enemy,
because in order to
authorize a nuclear strike,
there is one person, and one
person only who can do it,
and that is, of course, the president.
The president's call with orders
to strike would then be processed
for the US Strategic Air Command,
which is located at Offutt
Air Force Base in Nebraska.
(bright music continues)
This location was chosen because
it is roughly in the middle
of the country and sits
well beyond the range
of hostile missiles or
nuclear armed bombers.
From this command center,
orders are carried out
to complete the strike
using any capability
of the US Nuclear Triad,
because the US has three main
ways in which it can launch
a nuclear strike, from land
using intercontinental missiles,
from the sea using nuclear submarines,
or from the air using bombers.
(bright music)
So this is the chain of command used
to launch nuclear strikes in the US.
But there is one big
problem with this logic,
because all of this only works effectively
if the US launches the initial strike.
But what if another nation
strikes the US first instead?
A nuclear detonation releases a wave
of electromagnetic pulses, or EMPs,
and such a blast can take
out the electrical grid
as well as any vulnerable
communication methods.
This means that the
call from the president
might not reach its designated target.
Additionally, important command centers
such as the Pentagon, the White House,
or even Offutt Air Force
Base itself might be targets
during a nuclear attack
and could be taken out.
Therefore, the US wanted to prove
that even if they are hit first,
even if American cities, military bases
and command structure is wiped out,
they can still strike back.
This idea became known as
mutually assured destruction.
If any country does
attack the United States,
the US will be able to retaliate.
And so Operation Looking
Glass was established.
This is the name for a series of aircraft,
specifically EC-135s, that are designed
to take over nuclear command authority
should anything happen to
ground control at Offutt.
Its name comes from its mission.
It is meant to mirror
or be a Looking Glass for ground control.
And so Boeing KC-135
Stratotankers were stripped
and retrofitted with
communications equipment
to make sure they have the
same capabilities in the air
as they would on the ground.
But planes that are parked on
the ground are easy targets.
And so beginning in 1961,
Operation Looking Glass goes
on 24/7 airborne alert.
(energetic music)
This means that at least one
of these aircraft is in the
air at any given moment.
This way, even if the
entire Looking Glass fleet
is destroyed, there will still
always be at least one EC-135
in the air that can take
over nuclear command.
(bright music)
What is almost unbelievable to me
is that this airborne alert lasted
for a staggering 29
years, from 1961 to 1990.
For any given moment, day
or night, of those 29 years
of US history, there always
was at least one EC-135
in the air ready to
launch a nuclear strike.
Only in 1990, just as the
Cold War was cooling down,
the constant airborne alert was halted.
But even then, there's still
always at least one plane
that remains ready to
take off within minutes.
Eventually in the 1970s, these
EC-135 aircraft were replaced
by a more modern Boeing
747-200s, retrofitted with all
of the communications equipment needed
to keep the president connected
to anywhere in the world.
And these Boeing 747s make
up the Doomsday Plane fleet
that is still being used to this day.
So let's take a look inside to see
what makes this such a unique aircraft.
(bright music)
Towards the very front of the plane,
there is a command office suite,
basically a private area
reserved for any VIP
that may be traveling on the plane.
This is likely where the
president will take up quarters
should doomsday ever come,
but in practice, it is
actually most commonly used
by the Secretary of Defense,
because while traveling abroad,
the Secretary of Defense
typically flies using one
of these aircraft.
Just behind this suite is the galley,
or the flight attendant station.
And next to the galley is
a small conference room
where meetings can be held in flight,
almost like a flying situation room.
It seats up to nine people and
could very well be the room
where the fate of an
entire nation may be held
if the United States
ever enters nuclear war.
Just beyond the conference
room is a briefing area.
Here, a podium is set up
so that leadership members
can address their staff.
There are also multiple
phones, as maintaining contact
with military units, government agencies
and command centers
around the world is one
of the aircraft's primary missions.
And during foreign visits,
this area also doubles
as a press room where
journalists can be seated
and press conferences
can be held mid-flight.
(bright music)
Continuing on past this room
is the Battle Staff Area.
This is the largest room inside the plane.
Here, several workstations are set up,
and you'll find equipment you'd expect
to se in a typical office
setting, like computers, phones,
printers and copiers.
It is essentially a cubicle space.
From here, the military staff
can track unfolding events
and can help coordinate a
response to a national emergency.
Just past the Battle Staff Area
is the communication section.
This is where the aircraft
communication specialists work
to maintain contact with
different military units.
The aircraft is equipped
with multiple redundant
communication systems,
and if one network becomes unavailable,
operators can quickly identify the issue
and switch to another system.
(bright music)
Also monitored from here
is the aircraft's survivable
super high frequency,
or SHF system.
This system is located in
the distinctive hump on top
of the aircraft, and inside
it, there is an antenna
that transmits very short radio waves
capable of carrying large amounts
of information across long distances.
This system is primarily used
to establish direct links
with US military satellites in orbit,
providing a highly secure means
of communication even when
other networks are unavailable.
(bright music)
And just below the
communications workstation
sits probably the most complex piece
of communications
equipment on this aircraft.
In the middle of this room
sits a compartment containing
a spool of antenna cable.
This cable can be deployed
while the aircraft is in flight.
Then the wire is reeled out
through the back of the plane
and it is trailing behind
it through the sky.
At full length, this antenna extends
a staggering five miles.
(bright music)
This enormous length is needed
to create a very low frequency antenna.
Very low frequency radio
wavelengths are absolutely massive,
stretching for miles, and to
transmit them effectively,
you need an antenna
that is at least some meaningful fraction
of that wavelength.
When this antenna is in use,
the aircraft typically flies
in gentle banking turns,
which helps to keep the wire stable
and hanging in a more controlled
position behind the plane.
Basically, the jet has to
carefully fly in circles
while dragging the cable
behind and below it.
(bright music)
The benefit of transmitting
at these frequencies
is that they can travel
incredibly long distances,
and more importantly, they can
partially penetrate seawater,
which means this aircraft
can communicate with one
of the most critical parts
of America's nuclear arsenal,
ballistic missile submarines,
(video whooshes)
hiding below the ocean.
(bright music)
Two operators can sit
at the station to deploy
and monitor the antenna, and
a periscope lets them see
the cable while it is trailing behind.
These operators can then
communicate with the pilots
to ensure that they
are flying the aircraft
at the right speed and height
to make sure turbulence
doesn't damage the antenna.
(bright music)
Located just above this
room is a small section
with additional seating as
well as the crew rest area.
The Doomsday Plane is capable
of mid-flight refueling
and is designed to stay in the air
for extended periods of time.
If necessary, the plane
can stay in the air
for an entire week without
ever needing to ground.
By that point, the aircraft
could have theoretically circled
the earth more than four times
all without a single stop.
The only reason the plane
would need to land after a week
is because the engines
would run out of lubricant.
(bright music)
And just in case this rest
area isn't enough space,
there is an additional
one upstairs as well
just behind the cockpit.
One thing that sets this plane apart
from other Boeing 747s is that many
of the airplane systems
have been specially hardened
to ensure that they can survive
the electromagnetic blast
released during a nuclear strike.
The plane's windows are
covered in wire mesh
that helps prevent powerful
electromagnetic pulses
from damaging sensitive systems.
And even in a time of
modern glass cockpits, most
of the controls in this
plane remain analog,
another precaution to
protect the Doomsday Plane
from a potential EMP blast
that could disrupt sensitive
electronic equipment.
(bright music)
Everything about the
Doomsday Plane is set up
to support the President
and Secretary of Defense
if the day of nuclear war ever comes.
It is an essential aspect of deterrence
for the United States, and
these are just the E-4B,
of which there are four aircraft.
These are operated by the US Air Force.
(bright music)
In addition, there are also
16 E-6 Mercury Aircraft
that are operated by the US Navy
with somewhat overlapping
responsibilities.
Together, these aircraft create
a highly redundant command
and control network.
If critical infrastructure
on the ground is damaged
or destroyed, many of the
same functions can be shifted
into the air, helping ensure that orders
can still be transmitted
and received during a national emergency.
(bright music)
To me, the airborne lake
of the Triad remains one
of the most fascinating
elements of military technology,
and no aircraft embodies this
better than the B-2 Spirit,
a bomber so advanced that
more than three decades
after its first flight, it
still looks like something
from the future.
Capable, of flying at
high subsonic speeds,
the bomber can be anywhere in the world
in less than half a day.
(bright music)
My friends over at Mustard have made
an incredible documentary covering
how the B-2 was developed,
and they are using incredibly
detailed 3D animations
to visualize what makes it
such a remarkable aircraft.
They also just recently
started a brand new series
called "Unsealed", where each
episode takes a deep dive
into the design process behind some
of history's most ambitious
engineering projects.
(bright music)
For example, the second episode
of this series explores
the chain of compromises
and cost-cutting measures that
ultimately led to the crash
of a DC-10 in 1979.
"Unsealed" is available to
watch exclusively on Nebula,
which is also where I
have released several
of my own exclusive documentaries.
So many creators you
probably already watch
are making bigger and more
ambitious projects on Nebula.
There are comedy series
like "Abolish Everything",
history documentaries like
"The Battle of Britain",
as well as short and feature length films.
Basically, I'm listing all this to say
that Nebula has way more
than just airplane videos,
but if you are interested
(bright music)
in planes, we do tend
to have a pretty good
selection of that as well.
If you sign up using the link below
or scan the QR code on the
screen, you will get 50%
of an annual subscription
so you can enjoy Nebula
for just $2.50 a month.
(bright music continues)
Thanks for the support,
and thank you so much
for watching this video.
(bright music continues)